Inventory of the Rev. Samuel Huntting Sayre, Jr. Papers 1874-1989
Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Special Collections, Earl Gregg Swem Library, College of William and Mary
Rev. Samuel Huntting Sayre, Jr. Papers 1874-19891920-1960
Special Collections Research Center
01/Mss. Acc. 2007.43
6.00
Personal, family and ministerial correspondence of Rev. Samuel H. Sayre. His personal diaries from 1918 to 1963, his sermons and notes are included in this collection. There are family and other personal photographs and many postcard and tourist packet photographs from his trips to Europe and his automobile trips from California to Virginia. Publication material includes church bulletins, news clippings, tourist pamphlets, magazines and others. His family correspondence possibly has more personal information than his diaries. His diaries are often a day by day recap of what he did, sometimes about how he felt about people, places or things and rarely about any personal struggles. The family files contain genealogical information of the Sayre, Renison, Carmalt and Morris Families. His ministry work is detailed in his letters, diaries and other materials.
Sayre, Samuel Huntting, Jr., December 18, 1893 to after 1980; Sayre, Marjorie Renison, March 27, 1920 to unknown arrangement
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open to all researchers.
Acquisition Information
The materials were acquired by Special Collections Research Center on 00/00/2007.
Biographical Note
Samuel H. Sayre, Jr. was born in Hampton, Virginia, the son of Annie Woolsey Morris and Samuel H. Sayre, Sr. He is descended from Lewis Morris, a Signer of the Declaration of Independence. He served in the Hospital Corp Service of the Navy until August 28, 1919 when he began his studies to be an Episcopal priest. On September 18, 1919, he entered St. Stephen's College, Annandale-on-Hudson and graduated in spring 1922. Between September 26, 1922 and spring 1925, he studied at the General Theological Seminary in New York City as a candidate for the ministry and as a postulant of Bishop Burleson, spending the summers in the Mission field of South Dakota.
He served as a priest in South Dakota, Chicago, Pennsylvania, California and Virginia. He married Marjorie Mae Renison on January 13, 1934 in St. John's Church, Hampton, Virginia. His parish of St. Barnabas in Eagle Rock, Los Angeles, California was begun by his wife's Grandfather, Canon Renison, as a Mission Church and Rev. Sayre took over the Parish from his Father-in-Law, Rev. George Edward Renison.
Dates and Parishes:
August 2, 1925 to April 1927
St. James Mission in Mobridge, South Dakota (Rev. Sayre's first parish),
April, 1927 to January 31, 1928
St. Paul's Church in Kenwood, Chicago,
April 1, 1928 to September 30, 1938
St. Mary's Episcopal Church, Williamsport, Pennsylvania and The Church of Our Savior in Montoursville, Pennsylvania,
October 1, 1938 to October 1, 1939
St. John's Episcopal Church, Bellefonte, Pennsylvania,
October 15, 1939 to January 15, 1961
St. Barnabas' Church, Eagle Rock, Los Angeles, California,
February 1, 1961
Kingston Parish, Mathews, Virginia and
by April 3, 1966
St. Mary's Episcopal Church, Colonial Beach, Virginia.
He is a 32nd degree Mason, member of the Royal Arcanum and Sigma Alpha Epsilon Fraternities. Other honors include Dean of Convocation of Pasadena, 1955-1959 and
Chaplain to Bishop Bloy of Los Angeles, 1951-1961.
Scope and Contents
Personal, family and ministerial correspondence of Rev. Samuel H. Sayre. His personal diaries from 1918 to 1963, his sermons and notes are included in this collection. There are family and other personal photographs and many postcard and tourist packet photographs from his trips to Europe and his automobile trips from California to Virginia. Publication material includes church bulletins, news clippings, tourist pamphlets, magazines and others. His family correspondence possibly has more personal information than his diaries. His diaries are often a day by day recap of what he did, sometimes about how he felt about people, places or things and rarely about any personal struggles. The family files contain genealogical information of the Sayre, Renison, Carmalt and Morris Families. His ministry work is detailed in his letters, diaries and other materials.
Arrangement of Materials
Some of the material was already arranged by Rev. Sayre and his order was maintained. The rest of the collection was grouped into Correspondence, Family, Photographs, Travel, Personal, Ministry, Sermons and Diaries. When possible, material was organized chronologically.
Index Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Family Name:
Carmalt Family; Morris Family; Renison Family; Sayre Family
Genre/Form of Material:
Clippings; Correspondence; Diaries; Genealogies; Pamphlets; Photographs; Postcards; Programs; Sermons
Topical Term:
Episcopal Church--Clergy; Episcopal Church--Virginia--Clergy--20th century.
Detailed Description of the Collection
- (1)
    Series 1: Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1890-1989 (1)
    Rev. Sayre grouped some of his correspondence and these groups were kept as he organized them. Loose correspondence found in the collection was gathered and grouped according to subject: ministry, family or personal.
      Subseries 1: Envelopes and Stamps
    - Envelopes and Stamps, 1929, 1954-1964 (1)
      - Envelopes and Stamps, 1929, 1954-1964 (1)
      Subseries 2: Family Correspondence
    - Family Correspondence, 1940, 1952, 1954-1959, 1975 (1, 2)
      Correspondence between family members of Rev. Samuel Sayre.
      - Mrs. Marjorie Sayre, 1940, 1952, 1956 and 1959 (1, 2)
        Letters to, from and about Mrs. Samuel H. Sayre (Marjorie).
        Letter from Marjorie to her Mother. September 1940.
        Thank you letter from the Woman's Auxiliary of the Church of Our Saviour to Mrs. Sayre for her talk. October 9, 1952.
        Letter from Bishop Francis Eric Bloy of Los Angeles to Mrs. Samuel H. Sayre telling her she is a recipient of the Bishop's annual award for outstanding laymen of the diocese. October 1, 1956.
        Invitation from Chaplains Service Corps to a tea honoring Mrs. Samuel H. Sayre, President of the Chaplains Service Corps. February 24, 1959.
      - Trips Abroad, 1954-1958 (1, 2, 3)
        Letters to and from Family Members of Samuel H. Sayre.
      - Visit to Sierra Vista, Arizona, October to December 1975 (1, 2, 4)
        These are letters Samuel H. Sayre or his wife, Marjorie Sayre, wrote to his sisters, Ruth and Margaret, from Sierra Vista, Arizona. They go into great detail about his day to day activities. He writes about his family, particularly Ted and Margaret Morris who live in Sierra Vista, Grassfield, and the church. These letters were organized by Samuel H. Sayre.
      - To and From Family Members (1, 2, 5)
        These letters were found loose during accessioning and grouped A-Z by last name.
      Subseries 3: Family, Early Years, Correspondence
    - Family, Early Years, Correspondence, 1906, 1910-11, 1932 (1, 3)
      These letters were tied together with a red ribbon. They are early family correspondence between Samuel H. Sayre and his family and between members of his family.
      - Summer 1906 (1, 3, 6)
        In an envelope postmarked 1906 are postcards and letters from Samuel H. Sayre, Jr. to his family while he is visiting relatives in Germantown, Pennsylvania and at Camp Choconut in Friendsville, Pennsylvania during the summer of 1906.
      - Winter 1910 and 1911 (1, 3, 7)
        Letters and post cards from Samuel H. Sayre, Jr. to his family while visiting Aunt Caroline Morris and Aunt Minnie (Mary Cox Morris)in Washington, D.C. Tells about his sightseeing trips, visits to friends and other activities in and around Washington D.C. December 1910 and January 1911
      - Undated (1, 3, 8)
        Envelope with note: "Answers from Alice May Berry when I asked her if she loved me"¦Spring or summer of 1932 at ten years of age."
      Subseries 4: Family, Marjorie Sayre, Correspondence
    - Family, Marjorie Sayre, Correspondence, 1928-1930, 1932-1934, 1963-1964 (1, 4)
      These are letters to Rev. Samuel H. Sayre from his wife, Marjorie Sayre. This group of correspondence is filed in chronological order.
      - 1928 (1, 4, 9)
        Marjorie is in Eagle Rock, California and Samuel is in Williamsport, Pennsylvania.
      - 1929 (1, 4, 10)
      - 1930 (1, 4, 11)
      - 1931 (1, 4, 12)
      - 1932 (1, 4, 13)
      - 1933 (1, 4, 14)
        On September 1, 1933, Marjorie writes that her family and others "fell quite in love with you" and asks how he liked his first trip to California.
        On December 23, 1933, Marjorie writes of wedding plans for Saturday, the 13th.
      - 1934 (1, 4, 15)
        April 15, 1934 Marjorie talks about how difficult it is to leave her Mother and come East.
      - December, 1963 (1, 4, 16)
        Marjorie wrote these letters on her trip to Eagle Rock, California to see her ill Mother. Samuel is in Mathews, Virginia.
      - January, 1964 (1, 4, 17)
        Marjorie is in Eagle Rock, California visiting her ill Mother in the hospital. Her Mother
        is buried on Friday, January 24. Samuel is in Mathews, Virginia.
      - February - March 1964 (1, 4, 18)
        Marjorie is in Eagle Rock, California until mid-March. Samuel is in Mathews, Virginia.
      Subseries 5: Family and Family Matters Correspondence
    - Family and Family Matters Correspondence, 1890-1989 (1, 5)
      - 1890-1899 (1, 5, 19)
        To Annie (Mrs. S. H. Sayre, Jr.) c/o Thos (Thomas) Moore in Fairfax Courthouse, Virginia, from Papa in Hampton, Virginia May 6, 1891.
        To Annie (Mrs. S. H. Sayre, Jr.) c/o Thos (Thomas) Moore in Fairfax Courthouse, Virginia, from (Papa). May 7, 1891.
        To Nancy, From unknown in Wilmington, North Carolina. November 13, 1898.
      - 1900-1909 (1, 5, 20)
        Empty envelope from S.H. Sayre, Jr. of Hampton, Virginia to Miss Caroline P. Morris in Scarsdale, New York. Postmarked January 3, 1909.
      - 1910 -1919 (1, 5, 21)
        Some of these letters are between other members of the family.
        Letters from Samuel H. Sayre's Mother and Father, his Aunt Caroline P. Morris, Aunt Minnie, Aunt Mary Cox Sayre, Morris Sayre, Uncle Charles R. Sayre, Frances R. Vance of Department of Charities in Los Angeles, California.
        Letter to Samuel H. Sayre from his brother, Morris Sayre, where Morris gives advice to Sam about what his next step in life should be, particularly pursuing the ministry. May 7, 1914.
      - 1920-1929 (1, 5, 22)
        Some of these letters are between other family members or letters that Samuel H. Sayre wrote to family members. Correspondents include Samuel H. Sayre's Mother, his brother, Morris Sayre and Aunts Minnie and Caroline. Most letters do not have envelopes, but in 1923 Samuel H. Sayre was living in Hampton and at the General Theological Seminary in New York City.
        In July 10, 1922 letter to Aunts (Aunt Minnie) while he is in Dupree, South Dakota, Samuel H. Sayre talks in depth of his experience with the Indians.
        A group of letters from late 1924 and early 1925 with his brother, Morris Sayre, are labeled "arguments and correspondence with Morris 1924-25" and concern their philosophy on what is needed to be a good minister.
        Letter from Morris Sayre to Samuel H. Sayre where he congratulates Sam on his upcoming ordination. March 13, 1926
        November 24, 1926 wedding invitation of Aileen Harriet Elizabeth Renison to Armistead Claiborne Leigh, Jr. at St. Barnabas Episcopal Church in Eagle Rock, California.
      - 1930-1939 (1, 5, 23)
        Letters from Samuel H. Sayre's Mother, Morris Sayre, Marjorie Sayre, Read Sayre
        Letter from Read Sayre enclosing a typed poem The Passing of the Backhouse by James Whitcomb Riley. October 23, 1933
        Letter from Samuel H. Sayre's Mother about Marjorie's visit. April 17, 1934.
        A letter from someone in Hampton, either a child or a mentally handicapped person, to his mother. April 30, 1939. (Possibly Rev. Sayre's younger brother, Daniel, who was institutionalized).
        McClellan Wilson, Jr., M.D. wrote to Rev. Sayre about the death of Rev. Sayre's brother, Daniel Sayre. September 12, 1939.
      - 1940-1949 (1, 5, 24)
        Many letters are from Samuel Sayre's Mother who is partially, then almost totally blind.
        Some of the 1946 and 1947 letters between Samuel Sayre and his brother, Morris Sayre, concern their disagreement on their Mother's care by their sister, Margaret, and their basic philosophical differences about church and Christianity.
      - 1950 to 1959 (1, 5, 25)
        Letter from Samuel H. Sayre where he describes the death, on January 17, 1951, and the funeral of Rev. George E. Renison, Marjorie's father. January 30, 1951.
        Letter from Eleanor Searle to Sis and Ruth and to Sam and Marjorie about the death of Aunt Mary. July 1952.
        Letters from Read Sayre and about Read Sayre's death on July 9, 1952.
        Letter to Marjorie Sayre from Margaret Sayre Ransone, about Morris Sayre's funeral with attached note from Nancy Sayre, Morris Sayre's wife. March 20, 1953.
        From Bill to Mrs. Taylor Ransome (Marg) about the guardianship money of Aunt Caroline P. Morris. December 23, 1953.
        Church Bulletin from Saint Luke's Church, Montcair, New Jersey where it mentions the Memorial Windows Given By Sayre Family in memory of the late Senior Warden, Morris Sayre. September 19, 1954 and September 21, 1952.
        Letter from Bob Sayre about death of his mother, Mary Thomas Sayre, an aunt of Samuel H. Sayre. January 4, 1957.
        Letter from Mrs. Morris Sayre (Nancy) to Samuel H. Sayre where she talks of her deceased husband, Morris Sayre. (about 1958).
        Letter from Samuel H. Sayre where he notes on the top margin "experiences in (concerning) England and across U.S. on our return". September 23, 1958.
      - 1960 to 1969 (1, 5, 26)
        Letter from Samuel H. Sayre where he notes on the top margin, "concerning my call to Kingston Parish, Mathews, VA." November 18, 1960
        Letter from Samuel H. Sayre where he notes on the top margin, "last days in Eagle Rock, Calif(ornia) and trip east to Mathews-". June 9, 1961
        Letter from Samuel H. Sayre where he comments that he went to "Old Church" outside of Richmond whose rector is the grandson of Carter Braxton Bryan who baptized Samuel Sayre in 1894 and that he was elected President of the Thomas Nelson Chapter of the SAR on June 9, 1966. August 11, 1964.
        Letter from Samuel H. Sayre where he describes his past ministry and his new parish, St. Mary's Episcopal Church in Colonial Beach, Virginia. April 3, 1966.
        Letter from Samuel H. Sayre where he noted on top margin of letter "The beginning of the building of our new home". November 13, 1968.
      - 1970-1979 (1, 5, 27)
        Letters to Samuel H. Sayre from William M. Sayre (Bill), Ruth Sayre, Chabela (a niece), and Bob and letter from Samuel H. Sayre to his family.
      - 1980 - 1989 (1, 5, 28)
        One Letter to Samuel H. Sayre from William M. Sayre (Bill), his nephew. August 25, 1980.
      - Undated (1, 5, 29)
        Easter card from Ruth Sayre.
        Letter from Samuel H. Sayre's Mother.
        Post card from Morris Sayre in Turkey.
      Subseries 6: Ministry Correspondence
    - Ministry Correspondence, 1917-1980 (1, 6)
      Each folder in this group was either organized by Samuel H. Sayre, or it was artificially organized during the accession process. Some of the correspondence was found loose in different locations and the processor felt that gathering all the correspondence together would benefit researchers.
      - Church of Our Saviour, Montoursville, Pennsylvania, undated (1, 6, 30)
      - Kingston Parish - Call and Acceptance, 1960-1961 (1, 6, 31)
        These are letters from and to fellow priests and parishioners about his call to Kingston Parish in Mathews, Virginia. They are in chronological order. Most of this material was organized by Samuel H. Sayre, but a few pieces of correspondence congratulating him were found loose and added.
        Correspondents include The Rt. Rev. Robert F. Gibson of Virginia, Suffragan Bishop Samuel B. Chilton of Virginia, Bishop Coadjutor Robert F. Gibson, John Warren Cooke, Senior Warden of Kingston Parish, Bishop Francis Eric Bloy of Los Angeles, John L. E. Collier, Arthur C. Coons of Occidental College, Glenard P. Lipscomb, Bob Sayre, Rev. Richard I. S. Parker, Franklyn D. Josselyn, Margaret Sayre Ransone and the Vestry of St. Barnabas' Church.
        In a letter to The Rt. Rev. Robert F. Gibson, D.D., Rev. Sayre tells Rev. Gibson of his decision to "end up my ministry in Virginia". This letter also includes information about Rev. Sayre's career and Marjorie Sayre's family history. ( June 14, 1960).
      - Ministry, 1970-1980 (1, 6, 32)
        These letters are with fellow priests, parishioners, and others associated with the ministry work of Samuel H. Sayre. They were organized by Rev. Samuel H. Sayre and are in chronological order.
        Correspondents include Valerie Scudder, Edward Aupperle, Dr. Edwin D. Woodhouse, Louis L. Turner, Lillie Anthony Sutton, Marjorie M. Schmidt, Mrs.George C. Silzer, Los Angeles Council No. 1489 - Royal Arcanum, Boys' Home in Covington, Virginia, Bishop Stevens about Consecration of St. Barnabas' Church, Rev. Sumner Walters, Margaret H. Cook, Rev. R. G. Bannen, Rev. Theodore S. Will, Christ Church in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, Norman Stockett, Adele Brueninghausen, Bishop Frank DeMoulin, Bishop Beverley D. Tucker of Norfolk, Virginia, Margaret C. Thomas, W. Blair Roberts, C. E. Tolkien, Rev. Arthur C. Thomson, Rev. William P. Remington, G. Frank Shelby, Ethel Plass, Presiding Bishop of Michigan, Mrs. Skipper, The Brotherhood of St. Andrew in the United States, Mrs. James Stoughton, George H. Streaker, Mrs. William Vincent and Rev. George H. Thomas.
      Subseries 7: Ministry and Professional Correspondence
    - Ministry and Professional Correspondence, 1916-1980 (1, 7)
      Received in a green file box with correspondence in alphabetical order.
      Most correspondents' names are noted, but some are either too difficult to read or do not appear on the letter. The content and date of some letters have been noted. Even though there are a few family letters, most of the correspondence concerns Rev. Samuel H. Sayre's ministry, his church related activities, his professional activities or other personal concerns not related to his family.
      - A - E (1, 7, 33)
        Correspondents include Gertrude Jean Baker, George B. Baldwin, Barbara Barth, Harry Beal, L. Nelson Bell, Dan M. Budy, Cary R. Blain, Rt. Rev. F. Eric Bloy, Mrs. John Brearton (Virginia), Harry A. Brenner, Frank R. Brandenburg, Rt. Rev. Hunter Wyatt Brown, Bishop of Harrisburg, Pennsylvania, G. Braxton Bryan, Rev. John S. Bunting, Hugh L. Burleson, Bishop of South Dakota (Includes on heading: Rev. Wm. A.R. Goodwin, D.D. Rector, St. Paul's Church, Rochester, New York), John Burt, Uncle James Carmalt, brother of William H. Carmalt, MD, Samuel H. Sayre's Great- Uncles March 16, 1916, William H. Carmalt to Annie Sayre (Mother of Samuel H. Sayre. Dated August 7, 1928) and Dwight D. Eisenhower, President of the United States (Carbon Copy. Dated March 26, 1953).
      - F - Q (1, 7, 34)
        Correspondents include Howard L. Hamilton (made Samuel Sayre the Honorary Chaplain of the Virginia Society in 1979), Venerable Paul E. Langpaap, J.C. Morris (Transcript of letter written from Grassfield in March 1876 with two attachments: a December 21, 1874 financial document where citizens of Friendsville give sums for the erection of a Protestant Episcopal Church and an "Order of Exercises" for the Laying of the Corner Stone of The Church of the Holy Spirit in Friendsville, Pennsylvania on June 7, 1876), The Rt. Rev. Austin Pardue, D.D. Retired, Arthur C. Patterson, Jr., A.H. Patterson, Pi Alpha Fraternity and H. Boone Porter of The Living Church.
      - R - Z (1, 7, 35)
        George H. Randall concerning Brotherhood of St. Andrew in the United States, William P. Remington, Mrs. Ringsdorf, Reliable Furniture Company, W. Blair Roberts, Albert Rose, Royal Arcanum and Paul Rusch.
      Subseries 8: Ministry and Professional Correspondence
    - Ministry and Professional Correspondence, 1915 - 1979 (1, 8)
      When Group 1 was accessioned, the seller had removed, and filed separately, letters that were written by well known people, such as Harry F. Byrd, a Virginia Senator and President Franklin D. Roosevelt. These letters were returned to the file in A-Z order, but they are noted in the list of correspondents. Most correspondents' names are noted, but some are either too difficult to read or do not appear on the letter. The content and date of some letters have been noted. Also, some letters have a note by Rev. Samuel H. Sayre along the top margin where he gives an explanation about the letter or letter writer. These notes appear to have been added at a later date rather than at the time of receipt. Possibly, Rev. Sayre went through his professional correspondence and kept items that reflect the variety of his ministry.
      Even though there are a few family letters, most of the correspondence concerns Rev. Samuel H. Sayre's ministry, his church related activities, his professional activities or other personal concerns not related to his family.
      - A (1, 8, 36)
        Correspondents include John H. Allen and John M. Allin.
      - B (1, 8, 37)
        Correspondents include Rev. John Baden, Rev. Carroll C. Barbour, Bard College, Eugene F. Barnes, Wallace T. Bennett, Estelle Billups, Francis E. Bloy, Wyatt Brown, John Burt, Harry F. Byrd, U.S. Senator from Virginia and James F. Byrnes, Governor of South Carolina.
      - C (1, 8, 38)
        Correspondents include Hester Campbell, Uncle James Carmalt (brother of W. H. Carmalt, M.D., Samuel H. Sayre's Great Uncle) This letter includes some family history in an attached letter to Samuel H. Sayre's Mother from W.H. Carmalt, Edwin R. Carter, Samuel B. Chilton, Church Periodical Club, C. M. Clement, George H. Clendenin, J. Morris Coerr, J. H. H. Coleman, Maurice M. Copebaack (difficult to read), Charles Cove, II, Rev. Charles S. Cook, Jr., John Warren Cooke, Ruth Cotter (Mrs. Richard Comfort Cotter), Earl S. Cox, H. H. Cowan and Betty Healy Cutler.
      - D (1, 8, 39)
        Correspondents include Pierre Daltour, Thomas C. Darst, Bishop George Davenport, George M. Day, Whittney Diggs, Thomas N. Downing, Charles B. Dubell and Frank Du Moulin.
      - E and F (1, 8, 40)
        Correspondents include Mrs. William S. Edgar (Cousin Debbie Edgar), Eagle Rock Ministerial Association, Kenny and Frances Ferguson, David Lincoln Ferris, Rev. Frank Foote and Gordon M. Fothergill.
      - G (1, 8, 41)
        Correspondents include Roy S. Gaskill, General Theological Seminary in New York, Bob Gibson, Barry Goldwater, U.S. Senator from Arizona, Rev. Robert Burton Gooden (Bishop), Bishop Gore, Rt. Rev. John J. Gravatt and George P. Gunn.
      - H, I and J (1, 8, 42)
        Correspondents include Thomas J. Haldeman, Rev. J. D. Hall (a January 22 letter where he recommends The College of William and Mary), Francis J. Hall, Robert B. Hall, E. H. Halton, David S. Hamilton, Rick Hammond, Blake B. Hammond, Earl W. Haney, Bert H. Harper, M.D., Justice Albertis S. Harrison, Jr., Isaac Hartshorne, M.D., The Very Rev. J. Thomas Heistand, Gladys Hill, Hillspeak, Joan Hunley, Charles A. Junken, Edith Junken and Elizabeth Junken (note says, "my earliest sweetheart").
      - K and L (1, 8, 43)